<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title>Josh Fairhead - Systems</title>
      <link>https://joshafairhead.com</link>
      <description>Professional website of Josh Fairhead</description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://joshafairhead.com/tags/systems/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>Systematics Interface</title>
          <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Josh Fairhead</author>
          <link>https://joshafairhead.com/portfolio/software/systematics-interface/</link>
          <guid>https://joshafairhead.com/portfolio/software/systematics-interface/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://joshafairhead.com/portfolio/software/systematics-interface/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;joshafairhead.com&#x2F;portfolio&#x2F;software&#x2F;systematics-interface&#x2F;artefacts&#x2F;screenshot.png#no-hover&quot; alt=&quot;screenshot&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why&quot;&gt;Why&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The field of arteficial intelligence is complex and solving any singular aspect is unlikely to be of much much value due to the non-linear and highly systemic nature of these systems. If we want safe performant systems then we need to work cross functionally across domains like interpretability, representation, and steerability.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how&quot;&gt;How&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inter-related nature of complex problems requires a relational approach, which in this case would be a functional linguistic ontology. Without going too deep into his work, Bennett offers a set of ontological lenses through a set of complete graphs which link the stable or invarient elements of a vocabulary together as a sort of ‘natural language metaphysics’ enabling such elements to be qualatively transformed according to the mathmatical principals of applied category theory. In other words, to over come issues with representation and interpretability, we are creating structured systems of transformation (morphisms and functors) which are applicable to both qualative and quantative domains, represented visually as complete graphs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what&quot;&gt;What&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In concrete terms, we are using number to articulate graphs that recursively contain other numeric systems. We start with a series of numbers - which have a particular isomorphic quality - and turn them into graphs. Each graph encapsulates further systems as indexed nodes; in other words each node in the graph is indexed with a number that in turn represents the embedding of another system in the form of a complete graph. For example the number four represents a tetradic K4 graph, which in turn contains nodes representing systems 1-4, so clicking the third node would open up a K3 triadic interface with a new set of terms.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;horizon-1&quot;&gt;Horizon 1&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The backend is intended to be extensible through category theory and bootstraps from three basic categories; topology, geometry, vocaublary - all of which are delivered over an API. These categories are complete in so far as they are enough to create an interface for autopoietic improvement; building out the grammars of each domain but they barely scratch the surface of the possibility space. In other words we can use the API to create an index, plot them as nodes on a graph (semantic positioning) and then represent the core vocabulary in line with these semantics.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;horizon-2&quot;&gt;Horizon 2&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creates a functional foundation for further bootstrapping a more complete epistemology with hermenutic consistency based on the concrete significance of number. With this backbone in place we can then begin to add new categroical schemas to the system, be those maps of mathmatical spaces or Bennetts own work categorising science, philosophy, society and cosmology - which is obviously low hanging fruit:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;!---
TODO: Gallery of these images:
---&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;joshafairhead.com&#x2F;portfolio&#x2F;software&#x2F;systematics-interface&#x2F;artefacts&#x2F;12LevelsOfBeing.png#no-hover&quot; alt=&quot;12levelsofbeing&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;joshafairhead.com&#x2F;portfolio&#x2F;software&#x2F;systematics-interface&#x2F;artefacts&#x2F;12Energies.jpg#no-hover&quot; alt=&quot;12levelsofenergy&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;joshafairhead.com&#x2F;portfolio&#x2F;software&#x2F;systematics-interface&#x2F;artefacts&#x2F;12values.jpg#no-hover&quot; alt=&quot;12levelsofvalues&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;joshafairhead.com&#x2F;portfolio&#x2F;software&#x2F;systematics-interface&#x2F;artefacts&#x2F;12LevelsOfSociety.png#no-hover&quot; alt=&quot;12LevelsOfSociety&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;horizon-3&quot;&gt;Horizon 3&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the ability to create, read, update and delete new schemas such as above - we can start to work on the more category theoretic elements to the system, namely the various transformation types between ‘objects’ like the indexes, coordinates or terms contained in the bootstrapping ‘categories’ of topology, geometry and vocabulary. These are perhaps not as fleshed out as the schemas developed by Bennett (above) so those might be considered more useful for analysing the relatioships.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ability to add vocabulary and grammars in such a consistent way opens up many possible use cases in domains like interpretability, representation, steerability, and so on - for example, allowing us to probe latent space with different yet equivelent vocabularies in order to get a sense of an LLMs circuits, or we can link together knowledge graphs for the purposes of reasoning and explainability.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regards to the category theoretic elements, with our bootstrapping structures in place as well as some initial well defined schemas, we can start looking at processes such as the morphisms between elements internal to a categroy, the functors between categories, or the homotopy types within and across categroies that articulate a sort of state model or hilbert space (note that each system is itself a kind of homotopy type).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example we can examine the cross category equivelence mappings between index 1, coordinate 1 and term 1, which I believe is called the functorial semantics. Or we could look at morphism types between nodes in a given category such as isomorphisms, endomorphisms, homomorphisms and so on. We can look at linear transformations such as the fibrations illustrated below where the category of sub-animate existence ‘fibrates’ into a tetrad consisting of sub categories like ‘universal field&#x2F;radiation, elemental complexes, molocular structures, soil and ocean’, and the same for animate and super animate levels of existence. Or we can work out the non-linear transforms between systems such as from a monad of humanity &amp;gt; dyad of man&#x2F;woman &amp;gt; the triad of father&#x2F;mother&#x2F;child. &lt;strong&gt;(Note to self this is possibly a sort of qualative fourrier transform).&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;joshafairhead.com&#x2F;portfolio&#x2F;software&#x2F;systematics-interface&#x2F;artefacts&#x2F;3_TriadOfAstropoiesis.png#no-hover&quot; alt=&quot;screenshot&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;joshafairhead.com&#x2F;portfolio&#x2F;software&#x2F;systematics-interface&#x2F;artefacts&#x2F;12LevelsOfBeing.png#no-hover&quot; alt=&quot;screenshot&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building this prototype so that it is self consistent and ultimately correct by construction has already presented many challenges and bootstrapping issues, but horizon one has taken shape far enough to work on the API some more while adding new features.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;horizon-omega&quot;&gt;Horizon omega&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming that we get as far as horizon three, we should by then have a pretty robust neurosymbolic system. At this point, we can start to add generative AI to the mix, which takes a more cybernetic approach. Assumedly the foundations will be codified to start augmenting the small language models (different categorical schemas) with machine learning techniques such as supervised learning, evolutionary strategies and reinforcement learning. This is of course where the project moves from function into being, which would naturally need to be related to a will or purpose - of which there are many possible candidates.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;comments&quot;&gt;Comments&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is still barely a prototype but for now there are no blockers present and a relatively clear sequence of steps for it to reach its next stage. This has not always been the case and starting backend first led to a number of uncertainties. However having approached the API from the front end something has budged. We will no doubt need to go back and forth between front and backend as they both seem to influence eachother. Having the systems in the middle does seem to act as a sort of validation function for the more abstract work, begging questions of whats necessary and whats sufficient for the time being.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m very much looking forward to getting past the first development cycle where a kernal already exists and ML techniques come into play for the sake of augmenting human intelligence. This might go a number of ways but at the moment I’m dreaming of self describing protocols, autonomous cosmologies and holonic resource libraries that help us become better stewards.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We shall have to see what becomes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Resource Library</title>
          <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Josh Fairhead</author>
          <link>https://joshafairhead.com/portfolio/software/systematicsapi/</link>
          <guid>https://joshafairhead.com/portfolio/software/systematicsapi/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://joshafairhead.com/portfolio/software/systematicsapi/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;joshafairhead.com&#x2F;portfolio&#x2F;software&#x2F;systematicsapi&#x2F;HeptadEngineeringTemplate.png#no-hover&quot; alt=&quot;Engineering&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;Joshfairhead&#x2F;SystematicsAPI-v0.0.2&quot;&gt;Here is the v0.0.2 codebase&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The systematics API started as a way to store, preserve, search and retrieve the work of Tony Hodgson and JG Bennett - as well as other traditions that make use of such semantic structures. In short these systems are ways of organising information into knowledge ecologies.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its probably best to look at this initiative in horizons; so this basic funcitionality can be considered horizon one. The potential use cases of these structures in horizon two or three would seem to go much further than storage and preservation, but for now I’d like to keep things scoped to generic functionality rather than more visionay aspects of the work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;initial-thinking-and-learnings&quot;&gt;Initial thinking and Learnings&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the process of creating this API I basically articulated the various systems and tried implementing them in various ways. The simplist was through the Rust type system; enumerating the various systems and their values and then bundling this all up in a hash table. I then added an interface, which created the issue of state management so I rebuilt the state model but not the interface. The issue with this implementation is that it’s not very composable.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indexs, coordinates, terms, were needed to create the graphs, which were then constructed with a builder pattern. Doing this in state the ‘naieve way’ meant that I needed to articulate every permutation of index, coord, term and all the combinations of combinations (for links) to get the composability I wanted. While possible, this was not extensible because adding another object would requrie updating the state machine with exponential permutations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is basically where v0.0.2 lies; rigidly defined structures. I basically got it to a place where it worked and then decided to refactor. Following the white rabbit led me to category theory and some pretty advanced maths I’d never encountered.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current v0.0.3 attempts implementation by articulating base ‘elements’ such as index, coord, term as entries and then use link moprhisms to compose the systems. This is in the right direction, but is still not producting the desired results. Basically we have different link types that are transitive and&#x2F;or commute using the category theory criterea of Identity, Association and Composition. Connect an index, coordinate and&#x2F;or term with an ‘identity’ link to create a higher order entity - this creates a groupoid through transitivy (meaning that if I connect index and coord, where term is connected to coord, then term and index automatically connect). Then connect any of these base elements in groupoid A, to another with an ‘association’ link in groupoid B and all the elements should link automaticall through asymetric transitivity - meaning that connecting index in groupoid A to any element in groupoid B such as a coordinate or term maps all index, coord, terms across groupoids A and B.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This actually works as a proof of concept but it’s a blunt approach that requires deeper research. Namely that there are higher order structures than just terms and connectives like designations and coherence attributes. As far as base connectivity goes this is fine within a system, but what about composing across systems such as dyads &amp;gt; triads? or comparing systems of the same type but with different semantics?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A field of action starts emerging here; objects and categories, morphisms and functors. However when it comes to code, it seems to imply that category theory needs to be implemented before I can construct systems correctly and even then things are quite messy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance; if we compare a triad by Bennet and a triad by Landry we are comparing isomoprhic structures, with isomorphic nodes (though nodes within the structures are probably internally polymorphic). Now, the question about this is if such a morphism is also a functor? From the perspective of triad to triad, the mapping is isomorphic because its within the category of ‘triad’. However we are also mapping across the categorical instances of ‘Bennett’ and ‘Landry’, which would make it a functor.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not being a mathmatician or computer scientist I’m out of my depth to say how such people think about these problems, but it seems they have encountered a thing called ‘Russels Paradox’ which is a set of all sets issue. The uncertainty of which they seem to resolve by creating a hierarchy of universes. This set off a lightbulb because for some reason the Benned duodecad is presented as a hierarchy of 12 levels, so I gave that a go to little success. The issue here becomes both the rigid hierarchy and the infinite horizonal categories… the rock and the whirlpool.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rock represents the need for categorical hierarchy (the category of categories), yet the whirlpool resists because we have infinite possible horizontal categories where there is no hierarchy - such as index and coordinates (the categories of topolagy vs geometry). In computer science this dyad is stack and heap.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the question is how the hell to do this on a computing infrastructure built on binary logic?? Well from an earlier (unmentioned) excrusion of equating mathmatical operations to systems I discovered operation types such as ‘union’, ‘intersect’, ‘product’, ‘superset’ and so fourth - which all have a qualitive flavour. Having tried and failed to implement these, while getting utterly lost in recursion, I discovered another term in category theory called DSU or “Disjoint Set, Union”. Is this the monad of monads or even a nullad I wonder? Maybe. Then it dawns on me that Holochain as a distributed hash table with content addressable storage is essentially a DSU, which has generic types of ‘entries’ and ‘links’ as its fundemental dyad.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I’m basically still in research mode, but assuming that I can use entries to represent types of objects and categroies and links to represent morphisms and functors (it actully looks like the system may be built on category theory), I still need to work out the relativity of the various ‘elements’. In other words theres specific units needed in order to describe a system (index, coordinate, term = node) and there are critical functions that are not directly needed as part of the system, but give it critical funcitonality - such as the morphism or functor types.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, looking back to the heptad of engineering template, I wonder if this the research portion nearing completion? Is the next step imagination and&#x2F;or prototype? How does this relate to the octad? Have I mapped out the units as systems? critical functions as objects, categories, morphisms and functiors? The platform as Holochain? And am now working on resources? It seems so though it was pretty unintentional - even resisted.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;joshafairhead.com&#x2F;portfolio&#x2F;software&#x2F;systematicsapi&#x2F;8GenericOctad.png#no-hover&quot; alt=&quot;Octad&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
