<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title>Josh Fairhead - Whitehead</title>
      <link>https://joshafairhead.com</link>
      <description>Professional website of Josh Fairhead</description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://joshafairhead.com/tags/whitehead/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>Process Thought and Science 2025 (Session 5)</title>
          <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Josh Fairhead</author>
          <link>https://joshafairhead.com/blog/process-philosophy-5/</link>
          <guid>https://joshafairhead.com/blog/process-philosophy-5/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://joshafairhead.com/blog/process-philosophy-5/">&lt;p&gt;Session five is about moving beyond materialism, consequentially it encapsulates two core parts; a conversation with Ed Kelly (University of Virginia) in relation to Perceptual Studies, particularly centered around phenomena like Psi, and a video lecture by Matt covering Schelling and his contemporaries.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the ordering was as presented, it seems in keeping with the spirit of the lecture to reverse it and discuss the recording first before the conversation with Ed Kelly. By this I’m gesturing towards the key theme of Schelling inverting Kant or Fichte’s perspectives to arrive at his own counterpoint.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get to Schelling or Whitehead, Matt takes us on a historical excursion with regard to Panentheistic thinking - which is somewhat the idea of god interpenetrating the universe, yet also transcending it or being greater than it - because he perceives Schelling to be amongst the first Evolutionary Panentheists. The idea of an evolutionary process or time developmental universe beginning around this period with Schelling, Herder and Lessing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But to understand Schelling, and what was creative about his thinking or even Whitehead’s, Matt claims that you need to understand Kant’s Copernican revolution - despite Whitehead’s claims to being a recursion to pre-Kantian modes of thought, who he references none the less, and ends up inverting in an interesting way, possibly prefigured by Schelling.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s made clear that Whitehead probably wasn’t reading a whole bunch of Schelling, but he is cited a number of times in the concept of nature. It’s also suggested that Whitehead possibly got German Idealism wrong or misunderstood it, as he claims it was out of touch with modern science. You might say this about some but not Goethe and Schelling who actually contributed to scientific development, later influencing Oersted and Faraday, who developed theories of electromagnetism and were influenced by Schelling’s understanding of polarities in the natural world.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;kant&quot;&gt;Kant&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to Kant, in his critique of pure reason, he is known to have said that “I had to deny knowledge in order to make room for faith”; in other words that to know true reality one has to put aside materialistic science. However, Matt suggests that there is this ‘Kantian moment’ (or perhaps occasion), where Kant realizes that, despite his interest in evaluating Swedenborg’s Clairvoyance, Precognition, and other immaterial Psi phenomena, that such claims of disembodied entities persisting in space and time, required him to articulate a new approach towards understanding natural phenomena - one that would rule out and exclude what Newtonian Physics couldn’t account for.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is possibly the issue that Whitehead had with Kantian thought, or where he thought it “took a wrong turn” as Matt puts it. In my opinion it’s not so much that it’s wrong to distinguish between the phenomenal and noumenal realms, but seen as disjoint and separate there are clearly going to be issues with an excluded middle. This is perhaps why Matt feels this moment to be so influential; the disjunction enabling and perhaps even leading scientific thought to over optimize on the materialistic or phenomenological world view, while relegating the noumenal realms to second class citizens. It may be my interpretation of the lecture, but if it is Hume that woke Kant from his dogmatic slumber, it seems pretty odd that he would then double down on such a “Spiritual Disjunction”…&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to clarify this, I put out a message to Matt here:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;substack-post-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;Kant conceived of them as disjoint as a matter of our capacity to know anything about noumena, but as joined at least as a matter of our capacity for free moral action. We cannot know how we ourselves are free (since our freedom transcends our phenomenal experience of space, time, and causality), but we also could not know anything about natural phenomena without presupposing the freedom of our Reason. Thus theoretical knowledge of natural phenomena presupposes the practical freedom of the noumenal self.
&lt;p&gt;Not sure if Kant is where “things went off the rails.” Philosophy has never been a train track, but is more like spelunking in uncharted caves.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt; - Matthew David Segall&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;a data-comment-link href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;substack.com&#x2F;@footnotes2plato&#x2F;note&#x2F;c-175866026&quot;&gt;Read on Substack&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;&lt;script async src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;substack.com&#x2F;embedjs&#x2F;embed.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;script&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So within the Critique of Pure Reason, he’s asking the question of what our mind must be like or how must our cognition to be structured for nature to appear to us in a lawfully ordered way? As a student of Newton’s physics, and having done some astronomy himself while developing a “Universal Theory of the Heavens” in which the “Kant&#x2F;Laplace Nebular Hypothesis” is developed, they imagine how our solar system might be formed through gravitation alone. The Newtonian background perhaps illustrates the assumptions behind the question, which implies a separation that doesn’t so much hold water in &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;youtu.be&#x2F;F5awllN5W4w?si=58vHltym4BF4kjdu&quot;&gt;today’s sciences&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Despite being enamoured with Newtonian physics, he realized that if they were true of all of nature and the human being, at least in our embodied physical form as a part of nature, then there was no room left for freedom, just mechanistic causal force.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Kant wanted to be able to justify this “efficient” causal understanding, while leaving room for human freedom, he ends up in a compromised position. Matt apparently calls this the human interval because of its instability, where we are asked to live in two worlds; the moral world, and the material. The reasoning provided is that for human life, morality, civilization etc. to be meaningful - we have to assume we are free. Meanwhile the this moral world is completely invisible to the world of first order science, as it can’t be observed or measured. Kant apparently allows these to hang together by saying that natural science studies the apparent world and religion deals with the world of noumena which we can’t know anything about but are justified in believing that it exists; “I had to limit knowledge to leave room for faith”.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this is a useful distinction, based on the given explanation, I don’t understand how these worlds ‘hang together’ in this way. It seems as though Kant has made two neat piles and like Aristotle and excluded the middle where never the twain shall meet. I’m not sure if this is actually his position, so following up with Matt about this, he suggests that “our capacity for reason depends on our freedom”. This may or may not be Kant’s view, but it aligns well with Bennett’s cosmology where Hazard permits Freedom through choice (reason) in the face of uncertainty - which in turn gives rise to morality. If this is Kant’s perspective, it would explain why he was satisfied with his position and why absolutely nobody understood it when he originally published the Critique.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Matt, it took about a generation before he became all the rage and wrote two more critiques; the critique of practical reason, where he takes freedom as a postulate and unpacks his moral theory, and the critique of judgement which deals with aesthetics, our perception of beauty and also deals with organisms while exploring teleological judgement around purpositiveness.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;travel-gallery&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;TriadOfKantsBooks.png&quot; alt=&quot;Triad of Kant&#x27;s Books&quot; class=&quot;no-hover&quot;&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, Kant would say that there is a form of teleology in artistic expression because the artist has an end in mind, which they try to express in their artwork. He saw this teleology in the living world, and realized that there is a crack in the disjunction between the firewall he had erected between the noumenal world and the phenomenal world, which was the organism. The laws which apply to sub-animate existence do not apply to organism, which is where he coins the term “self organization” due to their cause and effect being circular, rather than the “efficient cause” of Newtonian Physics.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;travel-gallery&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;TetradOfAristotelianCauses.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tetrad of Aristotelian Causes&quot; class=&quot;no-hover&quot;&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, he was seeing organisms are purposive - as if Kant had said that even when we look at even a mere blade of grass, the freedom and self organization of our own rational capacities, our own autonomy as free beings, are reflected back to us as if in a mirror. He was seeing reason, which is supposed to be only in the human mind, in the living world operating in this looping form of causality. Where Kant goes with this realization is to say that biology can’t be a science because it’s not mechanistic, and when we see self-organization in the living world what we are doing is projecting our own rational capacities and freedom on to that. Resultantly, Kant believed that biology could only ever be a descriptive science, unlike physics which is explanatory.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hearing Matt’s account of Kant, I’m grateful for the summary of his thinking process and the historical overview. However, it does very much remind me of the Gurdjieff aphorism that ‘Man is third force blind’ because it seems there is quite a lot of polar thinking and laborious amounts of thinking required to transcend it; namely things like the recognition that life&#x2F;organism unites the material&#x2F;phenomenal and the spiritual&#x2F;noumenal elements of existence. These essentially say the same thing:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;travel-gallery&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;TriadOfKantsReason.png&quot; alt=&quot;Triad of Kant&#x27;s Reason&quot; class=&quot;no-hover&quot;&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;travel-gallery&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;TriadOfAstropoiesis.png&quot; alt=&quot;Triad of Astropoiesis&quot; class=&quot;no-hover&quot;&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is interesting here is that this seems like the schismogenesis of a kind of Spiritual Disjuncture in the sciences, when perhaps what’s really needed is a real transcendental philosophy or more adequately science that deals with the hypernomic&#x2F;noumenal realm? Spiritual, or maybe second order science, dealing with transcendental wholes, somewhat along the lines of Sheldrake’s morphogenetic fields?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fichte-post-kantian-philosophy&quot;&gt;Fichte (Post Kantian philosophy)&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving beyond Kant, Matt outlines that in the wake of Kant’s critiques - in his so called transcendental philosophy - there were a number of responses, with the first coming from Johann Gottlieb Fichte who wanted to further radicalize Kant’s work. Initially he quite liked what Fichte was doing, but for Fichte, it there was a residue of dogmatism in Kant’s philosophy. This is illustrated by saying there’s a point in the Critique of Pure Reason where Kant says “I’m not a kind of darkly idealist who thinks there’s not a real world out there”. In other words that noumenal word which he buried and marks with an X, definitely exists and we can think about it, we just can’t know anything about it, yet he goes as far as to say that it is the cause of our sensations, sensitive experience and so on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not entirely sure how this is dogmatic, it seems quite open minded to hold place for the noumenal, while also dealing with the phenomenal. It may be that the dogmatism was Kant saying that we can’t know the noumenal when such a world is really “closer than your jugular vein”. To me this hinges on what is meant by, or specifically the methodology of knowing, which may be defined in several ways but is typically understood as what Bennett termed as “discriminatory knowledge” - which would be utterly inadequate for a second order - or noumenal - science that requires observer participation. Based on my interaction with Matt, it sounds like Kant implies this distinction in his way of knowing (or at least Matt does) but he doesn’t seem to articulate precisely enough to be correctly understood unlike Bennett.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;travel-gallery&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;HeptadOfKnowledge.png&quot; alt=&quot;Heptad of Knowledge&quot; class=&quot;no-hover&quot;&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However there is a big problem with the Noumenal; Kant has already spent hundreds of pages elaborating that causation is a category of our own understanding, only to now contradict this by saying that the world beyond our experience is causing experience. In other words what was previously an immanent metaphysics (where cause is just a category of our understanding), was now becoming a transcendental metaphysics (where cause comes from a place beyond our knowledge), Fichte sees this and radicalizes the perspective by creating an omniscient metaphysics where phenomenal and noumenal worlds are brought forth by our own minds and thinking activity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matt suggests that this may sound like solipsism, but feels it an unfair characterization of Fichte, who when talking about the “I” - the a first person pronoun - he is talking about something that’s present beyond each of us, that our empirical ego or everyday consciousness presupposes. An “I” that neither you nor me possess, an “I” that transcends us from which the whole universe pours out of, that is apparently not that different from an Advaita position, which he would have been influenced by through the Schlegel brothers who were part of his circle of friends in Jena, who were translating the Sanskrit epics Bhagavad Gita and Ramayana. Matt suggests this influence of Asian philosophy and spirituality makes it unsurprising that Fichte would go in this direction.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;travel-gallery&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;BehindOurEyes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Behind Our Eyes&quot; class=&quot;no-hover&quot;&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on Matt’s explanations, it’s possible I’m misinterpreting the stance of these philosophers as I’ve not read their words directly, and from the descriptions it sounds like there is a mixture of influences present such that transcendental philosophy is not ‘pure transcendence’, in the same way the Fichte’s more omniscient philosophy has elements of transcendence in it, namely that while essentially sounding like a philosophy of mind, he is still attempting to make claims about ‘the absolute’ or ‘all’ which is a transcendental move. It would probably be quite hard for any philosophy to be purely immanent, omniscient or transcendental, because there is bound to be a degree of epistemic trespassing unless very tightly scoped to the appropriate domain, but instead it’s interesting to note the dynamic interplays between these domains which give rise to a particular brew. For example Fichte’s work appears to be a 2-1-3 “Concentration” pattern in the language of &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;cosmicecology.org&#x2F;page33.html&quot;&gt;Cosmic Ecology&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, where “A receptive impulse (omniscient) moderated by a an affirmative state (transcendental) focuses the scope of reconciliation (immanent) increasing concentrative power.” where the essence of German idealism was refined. This is however admittedly a somewhat speculative take from 30,000ft using analytical tools beyond the time in question.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;travel-gallery&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;TriadOfLandriesMetaphysics.png&quot; alt=&quot;Triad of Landry&#x27;s Metaphysics&quot; class=&quot;no-hover&quot;&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;schelling&quot;&gt;Schelling&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schelling appears on the scene in the late 1790s, initially as a student of Fichte’s publishing articles in response to his work aged nineteen, initially impressed by Fichte’s efforts to radicalize Kant, making Kant even more ‘transcendental’ than even Kant realized (Matt’s word choice, not mine this is possibly better framed as ‘omniscient’). This they called the spirit of Kant, though the letter was more conservative, and the claim somewhat debatable - especially as Kant apparently lived to see what they were doing and got uncomfortable with it (though admittedly his own perspectives seemed to change over time).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schelling, having grown up in the context of Swabian Pietism, was relatively at home with mysticism that made connections between nature and the spiritual with heartfelt faith, but Fichte was so intensely emphasizing the mind pole (omniscient) that Schelling too became uncomfortable, feeling that nature was not being done justice towards in Fichte’s approach in which nature was just the “not-I”. From Fichte’s perspective, nature is something posited by the “I” through its activity, so that the I can reflect upon itself and meet some resistance in order to become self conscious. In this sense it would seem that nature is naught but a mirror with no autonomous independent reality of its own, so a mere appearance and even more than Kant had it in his ‘transcendental’ philosophy (again it sounds like it’s more of an omniscient philosophy, that births a space for the transcendental by ‘negating the negative’ as Hegel would say)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;travel-gallery&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;TriadOfKantsReason.png&quot; alt=&quot;Triad of Kant&#x27;s Reason&quot; class=&quot;no-hover&quot;&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schelling does not like Fichte’s result, because in his view it is the wrong conclusion - nature is autonomous and has its own independent reality - not a mere appearance or mirage, and realizes that he can invert Kant’s logic to justify it as the body of the divine and a revelation of the deity. This is an interesting move because it perhaps indicates the kind of scientist Schelling was; from a first order perspective this might be considered analogous to fiddling with an experiment to change the results, but from a second order or relational perspective he’s making use of the relational dynamics inherent in the triad. At this point it’s interesting because by inverting the logic, he’s actually elaborating the transcendental aspects of Kant’s work that he said we can think about, but claimed unknowable.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words Schelling appropriated Kant’s basic question of &lt;strong&gt;what must the mind be so that nature can appear to it in the way it does?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, and said no, it is not mind and its categories and forms of intuition that are a priori (omniscient), it’s nature that is a priori, changing the frame to &lt;strong&gt;what must nature be such that mind can emerge out of it?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. This is what the author Robert Pirsig would call a “Copernican Inversion”, the moment that nothing changed but everything changed as Copernicus says the earth revolves around the sun, not the sun around the earth.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;travel-gallery&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;CopernicanInversion.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Copernican Inversion&quot; class=&quot;no-hover&quot;&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This inversion of Kant’s core question is what leads Schelling into becoming one of the first evolutionary Panentheists; he’s not an emergentist that thinks nature is subjective from the start, but develops mind out of this long evolutionary process that leads to the human being, in this way he’s quite anthropocentric. This is in contrast to the likes of Bennett, Margulis, Lovelock or Watts - who all see ‘nature’ as beyond human intelligence. Watts describes this eloquently as a planet that peoples in the same way that apple trees apple. Bennett would go one meta on all three of these and go to stars, galaxies and the unfathomable totality, but let’s stick to Schelling for now.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For him, rather than mind being a priori for the conditions of our experience, Schelling says nature is a priori and develops an evolutionary account that nature goes through to arrive at mind. Apparently he famously said that nature is visible spirit, and that mind or our consciousness is invisible nature. So his philosophy of ‘transcendental realism’ where humans, nature and perhaps the universe becomes ever more conscious of themselves was quite radical for its time. It’s not that nature lacks spirit, it’s that nature is unaware of its latent spiritual capacities and gradually becomes more aware of itself through ever more complex entities where humans are almost transitional state. It’s interesting how semantics of the word nature is interpreted by these authors, as it would seem that for Schelling it translates as an emergent or perhaps even transcendental whole in which we are encapsulated as a unified totality, while for the other authors mentioned the word nature seems to means a collection of stuff ‘out there’ lacking unification.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Schelling’s innovation is this question of “&lt;strong&gt;what must nature be such that mind can emerge out of it?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;”, where he begins without pretense that nature can be understood outside of his own conscious experience, which is still nature, just at a later stage of development. Paradoxically this means he starts at the tail end of the question, beginning with mind (like Kant), to answer a question with a different set of assumptions. Boiling our own self conscious experience to its most basic potencies he apparently suggests that nature begins with this basic form of subjectivity, which for him actually needs to be polarized. Without a comparative touch point or schema, ‘this basic subjectivity’ is seems rather ephemeral to grasp, though I interpret this as through Bennett’s energetic lens, with ‘dispersive’ or ‘zero point’ energy getting polarized into ‘directed&#x2F;patterning’ energy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;travel-gallery&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;12Energies.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;12 Energies&quot; class=&quot;no-hover&quot;&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My own interpretations aside, according to Matt he begins with gravity and light, where light is an expansive force that wants to expand into infinity and gravity is a contracting force that wants to hide away and shrink into nothing. This is probably the polarized state, with positive and negative poles. And apparently these forces never exist apart from each other, but are in constant struggle with each other, so he describes how these two infinite forces try to meet and defeat each other, and arrive at a series of temporary equilibria that continue to spill over and become more complex.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So he describes a movement from light and gravity, through magnetism and electricity, through chemistry to biology and on to human consciousness and self consciousness. Where evolution proceeds, searching for equilibrium that it can never find, and he thinks that by moving up this series of stages there’s an approximation to equilibrium reached, in say chemistry that wasn’t there in electricity and magnetism, and then in organism there is this kind equilibrium where there’s a sort of circular causality, where an organism has to maintain itself far from equilibrium but none the less maintain its form. So there’s a kind of temporary stability that’s preceded by this homeostasis, homeorrhesis is probably a better account to keep things in motion.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this evolutionary account there is a process of complexification that is not a random accident but a self revelation of god, which becomes evolutionary panentheism. In other words it’s an embodied spirituality, where the realm of possibility or potency constantly interpenetrates with the world of materiality; they are not separate, but one unified modality - in other words an Immanent becoming where god’s purpose unfolds. From this perspective the tangible spatiotemporal world is not illusory but the divine seeking to become more perfect and complete through a process of incarnation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;schelling-s-publications&quot;&gt;Schelling’s Publications&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point in the lecture Matt suggests a tour of Schelling’s publications saying he began in the 1790s with a few early essays that were responding to Fichte and very much in line with Fichte thought, doing “transcendental philosophy” beginning with the I and its activity and then trying to show how the whole world could unfold just from the activity of the I. So then in the late 1790s around age 24 or 25 he wrote a series of books on the philosophy of nature. Beginning with “ideas for a philosophy of nature” in 1797 and then the first outline for a theory of a philosophy of nature in 1799. Then in 1800 he wrote a text called “on the world soul, a hypothesis of higher physics for the explanation of the universal organism”, which got Goethe’s attention and Goethe who told the university of Jena to hire Schelling, who at that point as an unpaid professor age 25, became the most popular philosopher in Germany. It took a while for word to travel but in the 30s he was all the rage amongst the American transcendentalists, they were translating his work and publishing it “The Dial” and so on. So, in the late 1790s and early 1800s he really had this turn towards nature where &lt;strong&gt;he’s trying to say that nature is a priori as a dynamically evolving system&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, and human self consciousness is an elaboration upon a potency of potentiality that was always latent in nature.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early 1800s he has a Neoplatonic turn where he realizes that he has a Fichtean approach where everything spills out of the I, and that he has a natural philosophical approach where the I spills out of the natural world, and then asks ‘how do I coordinate the two?’. He’s realizing that he has two contradictory modalities between the transcendental and omniscient approaches and realizes there must be an indifference point between them where there is an absolute beyond either subject or object. He realizes that these two approaches he’s elaborating - the subjective transcendental approach and the objective natural philosophy approach (omniscient and transcendental) - are just two ways of coordinating our approach to the absolute and neither gets there fully.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He apparently tended to privilege the natural philosophy approach but wanted this to be a coordinate way for getting at something beyond finite rational thought (Immanent modality), because the absolute is the unthinkable and so the unthinkable. And so he was working this out for a few years from 1806, and while doing so, Hegel finishes the “Phenomenology of spirit”, gets the proof sent off to the printer just as Napoleon’s army is invading Vienna - though the proofs survived - in which Hegel criticizes Schelling (or is perceived to have) by implying Schelling and his followers think of the absolute “as a night in which all cows are black”, meaning nothing can be distinguished and it’s just a soup. Schelling, was upset by this and in a letter to Hegel requests him to ‘specify that you’re not talking about me when you make that criticism’ to which Hegel responds ‘I thought it was obvious that I was talking about some of the lesser lights amongst your followers and not you’. This apparently makes sense because when they were both co-editing a journal together some years earlier, Schelling used the same metaphor, critically, to dismiss idea by saying ‘the absolute is NOT a night in which all cows are black’. So despite the perceived spat, Hegel’s actually borrowing Schelling’s own metaphor, which led to confusion about this in the reception of the history.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hegel only became famous many years later, but from that point forward, Schelling realized there’s a major problem with this whole approach of philosophy trying to develop the system which would allow us to relate everything to the absolute (transcendental philosophy). At the end of the Phenomenology of Spirit, Hegel claims to have arrived at absolute knowledge, which Schelling was very uncomfortable with, yet possibly required Hegel to articulate in such brilliance to refute, because Schelling at this point started to say that the absolute or godhead was not a system but life; god is alive, god is freedom, &lt;strong&gt;and our own freedom is a reflection of that divine ground&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, and so the idea that that freedom could be curtailed and neatly wrapped up in a reified system, was horrendous from Schelling’s point of view. And so it’s not that Schelling gave up on systems, it’s that he basically said that each one of us needs to develop our own system - which may seem like a contradiction, so Schelling started to refer to it as his, while others needed their own so that it would feel coherent and internally consistent to them, as we all have this unique once occurrent perspective on the mystery of reality. The divine in a process of becoming if you will.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;semioticsinbrief&quot;&gt;Charles Sanders Peirce&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, wrote in a letter to William James, about how much he admired Schelling - because it’s not just that we each need our own systems, it’s that tomorrow me may need a newer system the one we had yesterday - so Schelling in Peirce’s view, was a very scientific thinker because he was starting again, over and over again from new points of view, trying to develop a system, but never being attached to a particular system. Peirce really admired this and so his evolutionary cosmology and panentheism, is inheriting some of Schelling’s insights while updating and reformulating the science, as Whitehead would also do. Beyond this we eventually meet John Godolphin Bennett, who once again updates the system and reformulates the best of what has come before, offering tools for making sense of this evolutionary search space while tidying up and integrating the work of those who came before!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction-ed-kelly&quot;&gt;Introduction - Ed Kelly&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, like Schelling I’m inverting this session so that the discussion with Ed Kelly comes second in the sequence, because the talk on Psi and such is more sensible when following this discussion about the noumenal world. Kant said we could talk of it but not know it, which to me sounds like the dogmatism he should have been called out on if it wasn’t Fichte’s criticism. In other words I believe it is accessible through altered states and mystic experience, what Bennett possibly meant by ‘revealed knowledge’ - 5MEO DMT is said to be quite an effective way to meet god, which I don’t doubt.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ed Kelly is from the University of Virginia’s department of perceptual studies, so is likely to have studied such experiences. The discussion however focuses on non-local, immaterial or ‘Psi’ Phenomena like telepathy, remote viewing and so forth. Honestly this seems better documented in “The Telepathy Tapes” which is definitely an area of interest, but the conversation was a bit odd and felt like pompous wise-acring without really offering much at all in the way of content.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of Whitehead they cover most of the ground already covered about actual entities having a physical and mental dipole that’s held together through the force of prehension. More dyads, but I suppose when you get into non-locality and Psi, that prehension is a pretty good term with relation to anticipatory systems. The most salient aspect of the discussion was the distinction between ‘eternal objects’ and ‘potentia’, the former being along the lines of Platonic forms and the latter being less symmetrically structured, so more along the lines of Wolfram’s hypergraphs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, this is all functional reification in my books, we can talk about Platonic forms but actually seeing the flows of our social graph and experiencing Psi phenomena is another thing, this is what I believe is the really interesting element of systematics - the non-theoretical application of Platonic forms towards a real practice of an immanent process philosophy. I probably seem arrogant saying this, as I have barely scratched the surface of the significance of Bennett’s work, which is more than just a functional reification of reality, but also exactly that; a sign trying to signify and gesture towards a Psience of the Noumenal by pointing a finger at the moon.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I may have been in a mood while watching Ed as I didn’t get much from it, but will go back and re-watch the discussion to give him a second chance. It’s possible he brought energy to the table rather than information and due to watching these videos in another timezone, I would only be receiving the information. We’ll see, but my initial impression is that it’s too fragmented to report on and there was little of salience that you won’t find in the Telepathy tapes so I’m gonna leave things here for now and possibly update at some point if the situation warrants it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Process Thought and Science 2025 (Session 4)</title>
          <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Josh Fairhead</author>
          <link>https://joshafairhead.com/blog/process-philosophy-4/</link>
          <guid>https://joshafairhead.com/blog/process-philosophy-4/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://joshafairhead.com/blog/process-philosophy-4/">&lt;p&gt;The session opens with the question of “what would a non-bifurcated science look like?”. Whitehead’s critique on the bifurcation of nature - the separation of quantity from experiential quality - suggests there’s no justification to make this kind of split other than as a shorthand to emphasize the measurable aspects of science.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words there is no separation between the red hue of a sunset and the electromagnetic radiation that the physicist would measure and talk of. It’s this qualitative science that Goethe was working on about a century before Whitehead, when he states that we are the most precise instrument for the observation of nature that one could ask for - not that either were opposed to using instruments. The statement would appear to be more of a concern that we might lose our sense of proportion by allowing science being subsumed by material instruments and therefore losing touch with life and mind, seeing them as unimportant impositions in a well behaved universe.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Already I’m seeing parallels with Bennett’s work in the DU1 which gives language to these concerns. He would say that they feared that “discriminative knowledge” would subsume “relational knowledge” and forms beyond these. To be precise Bennett defines knowledge as:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The subjective aspect of function. The ordering of function. Knowledge of seven kinds.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;travel-gallery&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;HeptadOfKnowledge.png&quot; alt=&quot;Heptad of Knowledge&quot; class=&quot;no-hover&quot;&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Goethe and Whitehead seem to be pointing at, are the categories above what Bennett named to be ‘animal’ or ‘polar’ knowledge. The exact category is hard to put a finger on without going deeper into their work and drawing out comparisons but these authors seem to be at least pointing at “relational” knowledge as indicated by the quote: “Human experience is an act of self origination inclusive of the whole of nature limited to the perspective of a focal region within the body.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this moment Matt takes a moment to clarify Whitehead’s notion of ‘actual entities’, stating that the universe is composed of actual entities, often wrongly identified as tiny quantum events which is not what Whitehead suggests. This is apparently because an actual entity is not a particle but an abstract category. There seem to be a few matters at play in this section; 1) an actual entity is stated to be an abstract category, 2) a quantum event is claimed to be a particle which it is not, (it’s a process of change from one state to another) and 3) it’s stated that in an attempt to avoid the fallacy of misplaced concreteness Whitehead engages in some extreme feats of abstraction.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Addressing these concerns seems to mostly be a language issue, because if a quantum event were a particle it would probably be an instance of the metaphysical class of ‘actual entities’ which appears to be a generic placeholder of units of existence. However a quantum event is not a particle and therefore cannot be an actual entity, it is more likely an ‘actual occasion’ in Whitehead’s terminology. So having corrected the premise, Matt is right, but only because the premise he laid out is faulty - or so it would seem.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wave&#x2F;particle, entity&#x2F;occasion continuum is not explicitly pointed at in the video but I assume this is what is being pointed at by the discussion on Zeno’s paradox, where it’s pointed out that our mathematical analysis of motion and empirical observations of motion seem to be in conflict - which once again points out the age old paradox of discrete or continuous reality. The take away here seems easiest to relate through Bennett’s Dyad; which is the notion of complementary polarity (rather than dualities that are essentially antonyms).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for clarity I’m going to state my own understanding of ‘actual entities’ and ‘actual occasions’ as complementary poles of a dyad that forms a class which encapsulates the instances of actual entities&#x2F;occasions as ‘particles’ and ‘waves’. This much seems pretty clear although the relationship with other abstractions such as ‘nodes’ and ‘edges’ are perhaps less clear.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently Whitehead attempts to resolve this paradox between continuity and discontinuity, through pulses of actualisation or ‘actual occasions’ that act as drops or impulses. At this point atoms are mentioned in likeness, but with the distinction that they are used in this context as indivisible wholes, as per the Greek meaning, rather than as parts. Rather than representing this notion of ‘wholeness’ as say a collection of parts, say a jar of marbles, a less physical notion of ‘wholeness’ emerges than the whole&#x2F;part holon, one that is similar to a scale free and infinitely recursive hologram, expressed in the following mantra:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Om purnamadah purnamidam purnat purnamudachyate &#x2F; purnasya purnamadaya purnamevavashishyate”, which translates to “That is whole. This is whole. From wholeness emerges wholeness. Wholeness coming from wholeness, wholeness still remains”.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, if a rich narrative structure is preferred to convey the idea of ‘actual occasions’ as indivisible or holographic wholes, we can draw on the parable of the Buddha and the Monkey King:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;_58XBCxg9Nw?si=n8uFKNrFf_RXN9w_&amp;start=512&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we might understand from these representations, we are not just working with one whole but a collective becoming that gives rise to new wholes, or actual occasions, where the whole universe is felt and unified in each occasion - bringing forth new perspectives that arise, endure for a time, and then perish. A universe which grows like an embryo and divides, like a cell theory of actuality paying homage to how nature organizes. It’s also emphasized that this collective becoming can be a society of occasions where many actual occasions are in a temporal flow that carries the past forward into the future in a process of concrescence (a word which essentially means to grow together).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The explanation given with regard to the notion of concrescence is that we have a continuum from physical to mental, or objective to subjective, whereby the physical pole inherits the prehensions of the past and is lured towards a subjective aim. Only some of these sensed possibilities, or prehensions, are actually relevant and the majority are negatively prehended (taken into account but excluded). The physical pole conceptually ingresses into the mental pole where the prehensions become what is called a superject, which subsequently dies to itself in order to become objective data in the future and repeating the process as a new prehension. This consequentially evolves ever more complex ‘societies of occasion’ where more and more possibilities can be explored, rather than simple repetitions of the past.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My interpretation of this is somewhat along the lines of the blind men touching the elephant. Each individual is prehending different creatures, the trunk as a snake, the tail as a brush etc. In doing so their expressions become a society of occasions that eventually concresce&#x2F;coalesce together into a superject elephant. This might really be a bunch of coders, mathematicians or hippies codifying their perceptions together, and in an act of collective becoming a new creation is born be it an application, mathematical theory, design or religious narrative.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of religious narrative, this juncture brought the discussion into process theology and Whitehead’s notion of God. The idea here is that the idea of God functions as the lures of feeling, the primordial nature of which holds together all the actual occasions and relationships of all the patterns that have ever been actualised - along with the concreted&#x2F;coalesced actual occasions in eternity. The claim that this is necessary in order for the laws of nature to persevere. In other words the primordial rather than consequent nature of God is the ordering and limitation of potentials. God here is an actual entity but not an occasion as occasions must be finalized, which an eternal entity cannot be.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having covered much ground here, it would seem that the easiest way to summarize the key points is to boil things down into a dyad of ‘actual entities’ and ‘actual occasions’, which give rise to dynamics of ‘prehensions’ that ‘concresce’ into a ‘superject’.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;PhilosophyOfOrganism.png&quot; alt=&quot;Philosophy of Organism&quot; class=&quot;no-hover&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;WhiteheadDyad.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Whitehead Dyad&quot; class=&quot;no-hover&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;WhiteheadTriad.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Whitehead Triad&quot; class=&quot;no-hover&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Process Thought and Science 2025 (Session 3)</title>
          <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Josh Fairhead</author>
          <link>https://joshafairhead.com/blog/process-philosophy-3/</link>
          <guid>https://joshafairhead.com/blog/process-philosophy-3/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://joshafairhead.com/blog/process-philosophy-3/">&lt;p&gt;Session three dives into the subject of panpsychism, starting with a quote from Heraclitus on the subject; which is that all things glow and have an ever living fire that animates them from the inside out. A claim that the world is ensouled, making panpsychism a sort of philosophical animism.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numerous authors throughout history have taken this view in various forms of course, the most famous being Jung. David Chalmers is another who brings this into the realm of Consciousness and stating that understanding everything from a functional point of view still begs the question; why is there experience?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently there is Michael Levin, who Matt explains has been driven to adopt panpsychism to explain the collective intelligence of cells which he refers to as goals in morphospace. No one cell can understand or perceive the whole, yet there is collective intelligence that shapes the behaviour of particular units. In other words a tail cell doesn’t know its a to become such but it’s morphology is none the less shaped by its community (or perhaps society in Whiteheadean terms).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in Levins work, he recently shared a new video called “Against Mind-Blindness: recognizing and communicating with unconventional beings”: https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=x9qb3bKREI4&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This video actually does a pretty good job of illustrating the definition of panpsychism which in the context of the lecture is “The view that all things, in all their aspects consist exclusively of ‘souls’, that is, of various kinds of subjects or units experiencing with their qualifications, relations and groupings or communities.” -Charles Hartshorne&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps the more puritanical view of panpsychism, which I think is perhaps over optimised along a singular dimension and so perhaps becomes a bit theological in that ‘we are all gods children, even the rocks and your toaster’. In other words viewed through the metaphysics of someone like Bennett, we can say this view is emphasising the “Being” aspect of experience, while ignoring the experential aspects of “function” and “will”.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I may of course have gotten this wrong, because the next section of the recording suggests that panpsychists - in contrast to idealism - generally resist the monistic tendency to reduce finite individuals to an absolute spirit or megamind… What cannot be interperted as a single sentient subject may be dealt with as a group or crowd of subjects (Leibnizian principal) or as an element in a more comprehensive single subject (Fechnerian principal). So while Hartshorne appears to suggest a reduction of this sort, I may be taking his words out of context.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So between Hartshornes words suggesting that ‘all is soul’ and the Leibnizian and Fechnerian principals, we get into a bit of a mess - and thats without speaking to Whiteheads god and process theology (mentioned in the next lecture) to the mix. This is perhaps dependent on vantage point, where a whole to one set of perceptions may be a part to another set of perceptions. Holons again, though it’s one thing to know this intellectually and another to experience it - which is perhaps Hartshornes point, and certainly seems to have been Gurdjieffs when he emphasized ‘being’. In other words - similar to the Hartshorne - I can say that ‘all is one’ yet without concrete experience I cannot resolve such a statement as I have many possible intellectual references (all is mind, all is heart, all is soul, all is XYZ).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the lecture goes on to say this is the combination problem; can minds be made of minds, higher minds made of lower minds etc. and like my platitudes above William James apparently suggests that we let go of the logical and simply accept that this is how things do actually organise. This reconciliation between experiential continuity and intellectual discontinuity, Whitehead apparently calls ‘Concresence’.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concresence as it is called, is explained along the lines of experiential units having both positive and negative poles. The negative pole gathers perished objects of the past which grow together into a new unit of experience or superject; which is a new subjective experience. This rhizomatic entanglement then perishes and launches itself into the future to be inhereted as an object in the next subjective occurance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of Bennett’s work this is what would be called Coalescence, which occupies point six of the Enneagram symbol - sometimes taught as the moment where ‘community enters’ which seems fitting with Whiteheads language and terminology, which explains this coming together as prehension, a sort of anticipatory mechanism (or organism) that lures these perished occasions forward into the future.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This nomenclature of “Prehension” can probably be translated into ‘pilot waves’ in Bohms world and hidden variables in the world of Active Inference, indeed you could also say the ‘grand play’ of lila or get spiritual mystic at this point depending on audience. In other words representation is a socio political issue that has a knock on effect with regard to the potential realised…&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point in the lecture, the video ends and discussion moves into discussion with Alex Gomez Marin on matters of precognition. Apparently Whitehead sees the world and life as rhythms, yet he and Griffin(?) are worried that allowing for retrocausility means the future is not open. To bypass this concern Marin suggests that perhaps its probabilistic, which seems fair, as the concern - if you ask me - seems to be falling into the reductionist trap of cartesian dualities, in this case the binary notion of ‘open&#x2F;closed’. In other words the future may be more or less closed at certain times and more or less open at others, such as the Yugas in Vedic cosmology.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marin then goes on to frame prehension in terms of an ingression from eternity to actualisation, which in Bennetts language would be the Hyparchic domain which lies between eternity and chronos. Marin seems to be on this point because he suggests the key to prehension is beyond the duality of unrealised &#x2F; realised, and should be thought about in terms of polarities rather than dualities.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex and Matt go on to talk about materialism and the mechanical view as ‘parasites of the mind’ because the notion that everything has to happen through physical touch rules out ideas like prehension (or hyparxis). In other words, they rule out non-local realism, and deny forms of knowledge beyond what Bennett would call polar or discriminative knowledge and the ordering of function to adapt means to ends.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marin suggests we must become artists, get high or read a lot of philosophy to bootstrap out of ignorance. However such statements still seem to be about knowledge, which as the subjective aspect of function is therefore unwittingly still caught in the paradigm that he opposes. In other words, much like this written recollection, the menu is not the meal - this is not the experience itself. We could actually get Whiteheadean here and say that this subjective review is the perished remains of a subjective experience (watching the course), objective data, that is now being lured towards and unknown future… Bohm would approve of such enfolding for sure!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally the hosts discuss Galileo and Locke making the mistake of trying to separate the primary from secondary characteristics; objective quantity from subjective quality. This is a fallacy that Whitehead demonstrates by saying that even quantitative measures like force are tied to and even derived from our subjective experience. Here its suggested that prehension (or Bennetts hyparxis if you prefer) is a metaphysical invention that lets us understand physical causation, affects, feelings, emotions, memory and perception as the same concept. That ‘feelings of the future’ are propositionsal feelings, conceptual and physical prehensions. In other words, that prehension unites the physical and mental.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this doesn’t seem wrong to me, it does seem a little loose and perhaps a little confusing without a proper grasp of the concept. Using Bennetts terminology for a moment, eternity (the realm of all possibility) is realised through hyparxis (or Whiteheads prehension) into chronos (temporal actualisation). So yes, all possible thoughts, feelings, memories etc. are moved into existence through this metaphysical invention. With that said, I feel that while Bennett and Whitehead were accurate and precise with their terminology, Gurdjieffs cosmic ‘reconciler’ is perhaps the most common sense and accessible nomenclature. Simple semantics but not so well defined… With that said if materialism is a naive teenager that got hold of the car keys, maybe this is the kind of simplicity thats needed?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Process Thought and Science 2025 (Session 2)</title>
          <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Josh Fairhead</author>
          <link>https://joshafairhead.com/blog/process-philosophy-2/</link>
          <guid>https://joshafairhead.com/blog/process-philosophy-2/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://joshafairhead.com/blog/process-philosophy-2/">&lt;p&gt;As far as sessions go, this one is particularly meaty - it begins with the question:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What does Whitehead’s philosophy of organism contribute to understanding how it is that we live in a physical universe which gives rise to organisms here on earth and perhaps many other planets throughout the galaxy and even the cosmos?”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this is no small question, and as the lesson suggests, the nature of this question has shifted over the last several centuries - where originally, indigenous cultures have tended to consider the earth to be alive with death as the big mystery - but now the more modern scientific cultures, particularly those possessed by the mechanical point of view, tend to consider the universe to be a dead collection of material particles; so the real mystery becomes: what is life?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The framing here feels along the lines of a dyad with complementary poles between life and death, which would perhaps be of more value framed triadically as a relationship between birth, life, and death. The descriptions of indigenous cultures also draws my attention to religion, which, like indigenous culture, often emphasizes the afterlife.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For mechanistic science, what life is becomes an inquiry of rather urgent concern, as in a mechanistic universe, the emergence of living organisms and indeed conscious beings such as ourselves does not make much sense. Living conscious beings seemed to be an anomaly in the mechanistic universe. The answer to the question from this perspective is seen to be rather bleak, with life as an improbable accident of order and organization that’s clinging precariously to a fundamentally dead rock.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps here it’s worth holding multiple viewpoints, noting the anthropic and the animistic are in tension with each other? As well as the observation that it seems to be the western view of life that perceives us to be in a precarious position.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Matt, Whitehead is ‘inheriting’ a speculative tradition that has origins in ancient Greece which speculated on the world soul and animus mundi, which brought life into organization from the macrocosmic scale, right down to the microcosmic scale of our existence here on earth.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whitehead apparently appropriated this Greek tradition not because life appears as such an animistic anomaly, but because physics was moving beyond a mechanistic conception, causing him to rethink the materialistic background which led us to imagine life as some form of afterthought or late emerging curiosity in an otherwise mechanical world.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The veracity of this statement is unverified, but if true would be somewhat anomalous itself due to the incongruence with Whitehead’s emphasis on experientialism - though if he ever said such it may be explained as a rhetorical tool to justify a panpsychic perspective to physicists and academics - or the essence of process philosophy as change and transformation is shining through, as we must consider Whitehead’s philosophy subject itself to change, revision and probably contradiction.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even in Whitehead’s time scientific materialism was proving itself inadequate for accounting for the emergence of life but even for our understanding of what &lt;strong&gt;matter and energy are&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Matt claims that by reducing organisms to mechanisms, Matt suggests that materialism ends up sawing off the very branch upon which science itself rests - which seems analogously on point if we consider those perspectives a dyad, though more specifically I think what is being reduced here is values to facts. This is almost directly spoken to as Matt goes on to say that for &lt;strong&gt;value&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, experience and purpose to be dismissed as unreal then the scientist’s own pursuit of truth, which is a value they are pursuing, is undermined along with the materialistic enterprise. In other words, it seems to me that Matt is subconsciously equating organisms with values, and mechanisms with facts - directly this makes little sense but when arranged as dyads and compared we can see they relate analogously and are isomorphic within limits, though not strictly so. When we connect the dots in this way our original question of the place of life in the cosmos is not disconnected from the question of how is science possible. In other words Matt’s assertion is sensible, but only when you have a comparative framework to reference.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its core, Whitehead’s invitation is to consider life as an integral feature of this universe, one that’s woven into the very texture of cosmogenesis. In this view, life becomes a process of coming to know itself ever more deeply in order to become more conscious. Again this is not too far a stone’s throw from Bennett or Gurdjieff’s articulations in the ‘five oblongonian strivings’, the primary aim of which is the conscious transformation of energy, incidentally a schema in which consciousness would be associated with planetary energy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, it seems particularly useful to circle back to Bennett’s apokritikal scale of being, as I think it can be a useful tool for distinguishing the worlds between experience and narrative. To avoid confusion upon introducing this schema, it becomes necessary to state that according to Bennett himself “being is mysterious” and so a scale of being can only be represented functionally by labeling the exterior or knowable element. In other words, planets, stars, and galaxies have an interiority that we cannot experience without actually being a planet, star or galaxy, much like we can’t know what it is like to be a rock or octopus - but we can subjectively name these entities. So in the following schema, ‘world soul’ is simply a more poetic expression ‘planets’ within the hierarchy - which perhaps offers a glance or inference at the interiority or being of Whitehead himself at the time of writing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that noted, Bennett’s (functional) hierarchy of being, or apokritikal levels, is useful here because it allows us to instantiate a list of ‘actual entities’ and reason about their ‘being’ or interiority in relation to other domains like values or energy. This also perhaps allows us to relate and communicate our own experiences of participation within such an animistic or theological entity. One of the advantages of systematics being that we can compare these exteriors across more ephemeral domains in morphospace like values and energy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;travel-gallery&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;apokriticallevelsofbeing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Apokritikal Levels of Being&quot; class=&quot;no-hover&quot;&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;travel-gallery&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;12energies.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;12 Energies&quot; class=&quot;no-hover&quot;&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;travel-gallery&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;12values.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;12 Values&quot; class=&quot;no-hover&quot;&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These schemas help us better understand the place of life in what is a reformulated and systematised version of both Whitehead and Gurdjieff’s cosmology. Matt claims that Organism must replace mechanism as the core metaphor of natural science - where I prefer to equate mechanism to the lower four levels of the schema, organism to the middle four and superorganism to the remaining higher levels.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly Matt claims that feeling - or “prehension” in Whitehead’s technical terms - must replace blind collision, which was how the entities of a mechanistic universe were thought to relate to each other. In other words he states that prehension in Whitehead’s cosmology is granted primacy in our account of causal relations, as part of a movement to give life its proper due in a now living universe.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He continues by saying that for Whitehead, every actual occasion and every atomic and animal occasion, is a locus of feeling. It’s a moment of experience that involves inheriting the past and anticipating the future, the degree, depth duration and intensity of feeling depends on the &lt;strong&gt;complexity&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; of the social organization within which that actual occasion is arising.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not that atoms are as conscious as animals, but in Whitehead’s view there is a modicum of experience. Matt claims that he is generalizing life beyond biology, rooting it in the very fabric of existence, as pan-experientialism, where to exist is to feel - however dim or simply. While I personally have no issue with this take, it somewhat contradicts claims made about biology being the ‘fundamental’ paradigm - unless the biology claim actually implies the biology of our first hand phenomenological experience? In other words we are organisms, and all our knowing is foundationally based in our experience of the phenomenological world, from this we can carefully draw on what we know and extrapolate towards a philosophy of natural science that may reconcile with what we can’t know from first hand experience (for a systematised approach along these lines see Bennett’s Book “The Dramatic Universe Vol.1: The foundations of natural philosophy)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sounds appropriately along the lines of Matt’s interpretation, where life in its biological form, seen in terms of living cells and multicellular plants and animals, is but a high achievement of this universal capacity for relation, where the cosmos is to be understood as an aesthetic process. In such a view, all levels of organization in the universe are artistic achievements, you could say artistic expressions. For Whitehead the purpose of the universe and evolution is to achieve beauty, in ever richer and more complex forms of beauty. It’s not a universe of mechanisms obeying fixed laws but an organism, a cosmic organism lured by beauty, with a teleology directed towards its production.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point we’ve crossed several domains, biology, experientialism and phenomenology and aesthetics. Each is also claiming to take precedent in various ways. This inconsistency is in my view part of the process, and we can ask many interesting questions about Whitehead’s changing perspectives and if there can be an organization to these different perspectives, as well as the cause behind his evolving views. This appears to be what Bennett calls in his second book “a hierarchy of values” which you might see as competing in realtime throughout this lecture.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next to speak in the value hierarchy is Love, quoted via Maturana and Varela in Matt’s book, where it’s stated that to dismiss love - which is an example of the aesthetic lure of the universe, or the erotic drive that underlies the evolutionary process - would be to turn our back on a biological history that’s more than 3.5 billion years old. Whitehead would extend this claim to say that, love or divine eros is not just the basis of social life, not just the basis of the biological world, but the very pulse of cosmogenesis itself. Bennett would agree, with Love positioned as the highest value, barring only fulfillment - which is associated with the unfathomable.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matt goes on to affirm that when Whitehead speaks of divine eros driving the evolutionary process towards the emergence of biological life, out of a simpler form of what we might call physical life (eg the rocks), this is not a foreign deity that stands above the world and commands it from without, it’s an immanent lure woven into the experience of each occasion as a call towards greater intensity of experience and harmony with other occasions and deeper beauty. In this view his perspective of God is not a cosmic engineer as the engineer was imagined by the first generation of scientists but the ‘poet of possibility’ that shares in the world’s risks as a fellow sufferer who understands and a fellow enjoyer - so the divine evolves with the world and enters into ever deeper relationships as biological organisms become capable of sustaining of that original divine impulse.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phew, this has become quite poetic which is commendable, there’s a need for beauty by Whitehead’s own standards but we may be conflating love with God - the latter being the totality which radiates such a value? This is perhaps a difficulty of expression, where looser language seems to be more appropriate to the higher apokritikal levels like the unitive love of galaxies. Using such a schema, we might express God as something like the ‘transcendent fulfillment of the unfathomable’.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But backtracking a little from such lofty heights, we must return to the original question of the place of life in the cosmos?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matt explains that for Whitehead, Life is not the exception but the rule, life becomes the very basis of creative processes in the universe. It’s not an epiphenomenon, life is really part of a grammar of existence, the cosmos being a living self-making work of art. He claims that life is how we understand the nature of the universe as an experiment in an effort to flourish, drawing new beauty from the depths of possibility. To study life is not simply to analyze DNA or catalogue species, but to learn how the universe itself is striving to enhance and deepen its experience. It’s about seeing how each being, each actual occasion of experience, each moment in the life history of a living cell or plant or animal or a human, inherits the deep evolutionary past billions of years in the making and anticipates novel futures which allows us to understand the evolutionary process as one where love or eros is infused into even the smallest particle or molecule and that the urge of creation is also an urge to relate.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such an eloquent articulation is quite frankly beautiful, and yes this all seems true as well, though this seems like priming for the deeper questions which relates to the autopoietic or maybe astropoietic process of cosmoi. Using Bennett’s schema relating to types of knowledge, this articulation is what would be called discriminative knowledge that expresses relational knowledge. The deeper question however becomes moving past relational knowledge into the realm of pragmatic knowledge, questions that seem to relate to the process of intentional self-creation, as well as world creation and maintenance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe this is probably what is meant when it’s stated that “against this modern bifurcation of matter and mind, Whitehead is envisioning a participatory cosmos, the place of life in the universe in short being everywhere, the cosmos itself is alive it’s an adventure of feeling, and striving for richer beauty. To be alive is not to stand apart from a dead material universe but to be the universe itself in its most intimate acts of self-enjoyment”.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be alive, striving and thriving is not necessarily easy depending on circumstance. What is clear is that the richer one is in relationships the easier this becomes as the principles of ergodicity come into play.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Process Thought and Science 2025 (Session 1)</title>
          <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Josh Fairhead</author>
          <link>https://joshafairhead.com/blog/process-philosophy-1/</link>
          <guid>https://joshafairhead.com/blog/process-philosophy-1/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://joshafairhead.com/blog/process-philosophy-1/">&lt;p&gt;This article is a reflection and commentary on Process and Thought lecture 1 - the content of which was provided by Matt Segall - a lecturer from CIIS that’s pretty well known for his expertise on Whitehead. This is my interpretation of the content provided by Matt based on his understanding of Whitehead, so whatever I say about his framing should probably be taken with a pinch of salt.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s interesting for me to discover based on this content is that I may be more familiar with Process Philosophy than I initially thought, as listening to him I immediately hear strong correspondences with JG Bennett’s work, an author who’s philosophy I am reasonably connected with and an author who seems to reference Whitehead a great deal. This makes sense given both their timelines, and they seem to be birds of a feather.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the lecture, Matt claims that Whitehead did not see the universe as divided and instead saw it as relational where every actual occasion of experience from sub-atomic particles to stars and galaxies is a unity of physical and mental feelings. Metaphysically, the echoes here are already quite familiar as he is first talking about an undivided, continuous or maybe Monadic universe that is also relational (or maybe Triadic). This undivided and relational universe however contains multitudes of layered occasions in a sort of qualitative infinity - broadly termed potential and actual - which range from the very small to the very large!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might consider this a paradox because if the universe is undivided, how can there be differences between occasions where the chair is not the table? This is a pretty old discussion and I believe the core distinction between substance philosophy and process philosophy. We can resolve this difference between continuous and discreet by saying that there are types and degrees of relation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Bennett’s work this discreet division of occasions or entities is broadly classified into categories called “apokritikal levels of being”:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;12LevelsOfBeing.png&quot; alt=&quot;Apokritikal levels of being&quot; class=&quot;no-hover&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matt claims that Whitehead puts biology and life at the center of the universe, rather than physics, which is a pretty strong turn of phrase. If you take the twelve levels in the image above and divide it into three sets of four, organised from bottom to top you get three realms: hyponomic, autonomic and hypernomic. These terms basically translate as material, living and cosmic. As you can see for yourself the middle range beginning with Phytovegetation and finishing after Humans denotes the autonomic realm, which essentially matches the assertion that life is central in these cosmologies.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be transparent about the epistemology here, the 12 levels that are articulated relate to the concrete significance of number which is further described Bennett’s Dramatic Universe - the foundations of natural science. Assumedly quite similar to Whiteheads process and reason though I’ve not yet read it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matt goes on to talk about how the biological (autonomic) world is a revelation to what’s implicit in the physical (hyponomic) world, and referencing the image above you can see that both authors seem to hold the same views once again. The diagram perhaps just enriches this a little and allows us to reason about the relationships between actual occasions by segregating them into levels and categories like the hypernomic realm, made up of planets, stars, and galaxies - which would in turn be a revelation to the autonomic world!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps where the terminology between authors diverges, because these levels of abstraction from the planetary scale onwards would be considered the more than living world or superanimate existence - perhaps this is where God resides in Whiteheads philosophy? Oh unfathomable totality, greater even than a collection of galaxies!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the terminology diverges, the views still seem to align and using these categories we can start to reason by analogy between worlds; what if we consider ourselves as atoms or magnetic fields, how do the laws of this level apply to say sociology? And how do our actions influence the heavens?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matt’s use of the term fundamental may seem confusing at first, because this idea of fundamentalism may seem like substance philosophy (think object oriented), but the contextual qualifier is that ecology becomes the most fundamental science because it’s about relationships between organisms. This seems allowable based on the principal that everything is an occasion and these occasions are ‘fundamentally’ seen as organisms. However, in order to avoid confusion in terminology I’m going to lean on the Hodgson qualifier and call this perspective a ‘Cosmic Ecology’ which refers to a form of second order science of relationships. In other words, maybe this fundamental that’s asserted is more of an understanding that’s based in the principals of rational ordering, relational binding and the process of ongoing realisation? This seems fair.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we scale these principals up to the hypernomic levels, it leads us to consider things like the anthropic principals (both passive and active) where we learn about laws of reciprocity and reflexivity - relations between stars and planets and even cosmic will. Going further into the unknown it seems we are asked to explore notions of cosmic accountability thorough conceptions of god and religion, because of course what kind of cosmology would be complete without an origination myth and rich narrative structure, as well as its existential grounding or law conformity?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This opens up some fantastic questions with regards to living cosmologies and moral philosophy, which is where some of the discussion about the realisation of facts and values seems to belong. Is there such a thing as objective morality? A second order perspective would probably allow for this, where facts are the realisation of cosmic values as laws, which in turn enable the realisation of subjective values. Fact as the realisation of value was somewhat touched on in the lecture, though I’ve pushed this a little further to express an alternative aspect of the ternary relationship based on Bennett and Hodgsons work, something that Whitehead may have also touched on - though I am not qualified to say for certain!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever the case, it’s clear that there is more to cosmology than the standard model, and I believe process Philosophy begins to invite such discussions, perhaps holding space between science and religion by allowing neither to become dogma!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
